hey what's up guys my name is the chato
and welcome back to my C++ series I
don't know what this hand stuff is today
I'm gonna be talking all about how you
should be creating your objects in C++
because C++ gives us a few different
ways we can actually create an object
now if you don't know what an object is
or what a class is you definitely want
to check out the video that I met on
that there'll be a card on the screen or
a link in the description below but
basically when we've written a class and
it comes time for us to actually start
using the class that we've created we
need to instantiate it usually unless
it's like completely static but what I'm
talking about that we need to
instantiate our class how do we do it we
basically have two choices here and the
difference between the choices is where
the memory comes from which memory were
actually going to be creating our object
in when we create an object in C++ it
needs to occupy some memory even if we
write a class that is completely empty
no members no class members or nothing
like that
it has to it has to occupy at least one
byte of memory but that's usually our
case we have a lot of members in our
classes and they need to be stored
somewhere when we decide I want to start
using this object I'm gonna create a
bunch of variables the object has a
bunch of variables we need to allocate
memory somewhere in our computer so that
we can actually remember what what what
the variables are set to and their
application is kind of added into two
main sections of memory the stack and
the heap now there are other sections of
memory such as the area where our source
code lives so by this point it's machine
code so there's other sections of memory
we're gonna talk about them later they
don't really matter right now just think
of it as the stack and the heap that's
all we care about right now I am going
to make an in-depth video about what the
stack is and what the heat Bay is in
this stack bus is behave and all that
stuff if I've already made it when
you're watching this video there'll be a
card there if not it's coming soon so
just hold on tight in C++ we get to
choose where it goes whether our object
gets created on the stack or on the heat
and they kind of have different
functional differences stack objects for
example have an automatic lifespan right
their lifetime is actually controlled by
the scope that they declared and as soon
as you as soon as that variable goes out
of scope
that's it that the memory is free
because when that scope ends the stack
pops and anything that was in that in
that scope frame in that stack frame
that gets that gets frayed now the heap
is is different the heap is this big big
big mysterious place where once you've
allocated an object in that hip and
you've actually created an object on the
heap it's gonna sit there until you
decide I no longer need it I want to
free that object do whatever you like
with that memory so let's take a look at
what the code looks like for both of
those methods of creating objects over
here I've got a class called NC which
just has a string now this string is
just simply a sanest Raina put a little
using up here just to simplify this code
a little bit so that we're not writing
STD string everywhere I usually do this
because I don't like using namespace STD
I know a lot of you ask me why I don't
like using namespace STD I'm gonna make
a video on that very soon so just wait
for it but basically we've got a class
with one member is a string and then
we've got one constructor which doesn't
take any parameters another constructor
which does take in a string as a
parameter and then we just set the name
to whatever the parameter is and then
finally we just have a simple getter
thing the name so I'll just made like a
little dummy class now let's try and
create it in the main function how do we
do that well the first option which is
creating it on the stack is very very
simple
we basically type in the type of the
class that we want to instantiate then
we hit the spacebar and then we give it
a name someone I call this entity and
that's all there is to it now because
we've written it like this it's actually
calling the default constructor right
this code might look a little bit weird
to you if you're coming from a language
like C sharp or Java in fact you might
think this this leads to something
called a null pointer exception or a
null reference exception because it
appears like we just haven't initialized
our object but we have right as long as
we have this default constructor here
this is totally valid code we can now
call and see don't get named and what
we'll actually get is well we'll get the
name
we'll get unknown in this case because
that's what the default constructor did
so
print this out to the console and see
what we get there we have it unknown
because what we've done here is actually
different to what this code would have
done in Java or C sharp and kind of will
kind of get there in a minute if we
wanted to specify a parameter all we
need to do is just open our parentheses
and give a name such as Cherno you can
also do it this way we can write equals
and then the type that's our constructor
done right and if we hit up five to run
our program we get chatter this time and
everything's great so what's the deal
with this when do we want to create our
objects like this the answer is pretty
much all the time if you can create an
object like this do create an object
like this that's basically the rule
because this is the fastest way in C++
and the most managed way in C++ to
actually instantiate objects now let's
talk about why why there would be
reasons where you can't do this one of
the reasons is if you actually want this
to live outside of the life of this
function if we had another function over
here and we created our entity over in
that function then as soon as we reached
the end as soon as we reach this this
this end curly bracket this entity gets
destroyed from memory because what
happens is when we call function a stack
frame gets credit for this function
which contains all the local variables
that we declare which includes primitive
types but also our classes our objects
and when this function ends that stack
frame gets destroyed which means that
all of the memory that we had on the
stack all the variables we created are
gone so let's write some code that would
actually fail scopes don't necessarily
need to be functions they could be if
statements for loops or even empty
scopes in which we just have curly
brackets like this if I've read an
interesting point uh now this is this is
basically a variable which points to an
entity over here I'm going to assign it
to the memory address all Barents the
object that we've credit on the stack
right over here I'm also going to
simplify this because I usually write
code that looks like this I'm going to
hit f9 on this line just to set a
breakpoint and we'll we'll inspect this
so right over here we create a new
entity object grade it's got the name
everything's great when I hit f10 to
move down you can see that we've now set
our 8.0 right so if we hover over a it
is in fact pointing to this correct
memory address in the name is cheddar
that's great
however if we hit f10 again and we
advance to this line and then maybe the
next line and we hover over look at that
it's still pointing to that same address
that the name is gone because that
object was was freed it was destroyed
gone this channel HD doesn't exist
anymore we were aged into the stack
frame it's gone that's the end of China
that's the end of that tremor go on
cellular that's good right so if we
wanted this channel to somehow live
outside the scope we couldn't allocate
it on the stack we would have to resort
to heap allocation the other reason why
we might not want to we'll be able to
allocate on the staff is because if the
size of this entity is actually too
large we maybe have too many entities we
might not have enough room to actually
allocate on the stack because the stack
is usually quite small it's usually one
megabyte two megabytes it kind of
depends on your platform and your
compiler but if you have this giant
class or you want to have a thousand of
these classes you might not have enough
room on the stack so you might have to
allocate upon the heap let's take a look
at what heap allocation looked like
so if we wanted to convert this current
here to actually allocate on the heap
what we would do is we would first of
all need to change the type the type is
now no longer entity the type is an
entity pointer and what we assigned to
entity here is new entity now the
biggest difference here is actually not
the pointer which a lot of people notice
it's the new keyword the new keyword is
K and that's gonna be video on that new
keyword very soon maybe even tomorrow
we'll see and when we call new and see
what actually happens is we allocate
memory on the heap we call the
constructor and this new entity actually
returns an entity pointer it returns the
location on the heap where this entity
has actually been allocated which is why
we have to assign us to an HD pointer
and this this is where you people who
know Java and c-sharp this is this is
what the code actually looks like in
Java or C sharp you would be writing
code like this so usually when you come
to C++ your instinct would be probably
just to change the time and suddenly
smashes Java code in c-sharp code and
you're right it does matter Java and
c-sharp code we just have an extra
option in C++ so we can allocate on the
stack you can't actually do that in Java
or C shop in c-sharp you can in c-sharp
there's something called a struct and
that's a value-based type and so that
actually is kind of allocated on the
stack even though you use the new
keyword but in Java everything's on the
heap and it's a shop all classes on the
hate the struct keyword is a bit
different than it isn't it's a plus plus
and one of the biggest problems that I
see is that everyone who comes over from
a managed language like Java or C sharp
just uses the new keyword everywhere in
C++ and you shouldn't be doing that for
two reasons and those reasons we're
going to talk about in that new video
because this video is going to be huge
if I talk about absolutely everything
but to cut it short performance
allocated on the heap takes longer than
allocating on the stack and also wedding
allocate on the heap you have to
manually free that memory that you've
allocated so once we do something like
this in our safe us+ code we are
actually responsible for freeing that
memory say plus boss is not going to
suddenly decide okay you're done with
this entity object it doesn't know that
we're done with it we have to tell it
this memory is free and the way that we
do that is we call delete and then the
variable name so delete entity if you
use the new keyword you use the delete
keyword to clean up after yourself that
is how simple sauce works so in our
example since we do have to actually
call delete to free this object if we
were to remove delete down over here
maybe even after this send get we're
assigning this entity on to e so we'll
get rid of this apps and we don't need
it since entity is already a pointer and
since NC is a pointer we actually have
to either dereference this first and
then call get name or we can use the
error operator which does that for us
gonna have a video on the arrow operator
certain I'm getting tired of doing this
but yet more videos and if we go down
over here we'll just change the late
entity to be delayed a so this is what
our code looks like now we create an
entity on the heap we assign and C to
this we're not copying any data here
really what
doing is whether storing the memory
dress the fantasy while copying the
actual HD object just the memory address
and if I hit f5 will be bugged this will
hit f10 you can see that it gets set
correctly we have our name sugar I'll
get f10 again I'll go to I'll go to the
scene get I'll hop on my mouse over in
you can see it still has the name
Chennai right because it only gets
deleted and it gets free here and those
are the two ways that we can create
objects in C++ and choosing between the
two is a matter of is my objects really
really really big or do I want to
explicitly control the lifetime of my
object if you answered no to both of
those questions I locate on the stack
right create or get on the stack it's
way easier it's automated and it's
faster whereas allocated on the heap
requires you to manually called delete
which can lead to memory leaks if you
forget to call delete I mean it's a bit
harder than just like forgetting a lot
of people think well how often you
forget to call the waiter people knew
you can you can miss it sometimes I
guess it's good it gets complicated as
well as well as will discover you can
also use something called a smart
pointer we're kind of gonna get to those
eventually and Lincoln that I don't even
know I'm getting really tired of doing
this I'm not gonna keep track of this by
the way I want to come back it's not
like I'm gonna come back to this video
in a few months and be like oh yeah
better fill in all those cards so just
search my channel for those videos if
they're there that they're for the north
panel but with smart pointers we can
actually kind of still allocate on the
heap and still get that kind of size
advantage but also have our objects be
automatically deleted when either the
pointer goes out of scope or maybe like
in the case of shared pointers when
there are no more references will talk
about oldest memory stuff in the future
I don't want to get into it right now
but if we're just talking about kind of
primitive C++ two ways to make objects
stack and heap
those are my recent spread on the stack
unless you absolutely can't do you guys
enjoy this video then you can hit that
like button and you can support this
series on patreon.com for such the chair
oh you'll get episodes early basically
as soon as I'm done editing the episodes
get released to all the patrons which is
pretty cool you can also discuss and
talk about what goes into these videos
and make suggestions for new videos and
all that fun stuff and you also help
support this series and make sure that I
keep making videos next time I'm pretty
sure we're gonna talk about the new
keyword so that should be exciting
definitely watch that video it'll be in
the haha I'm done goodbye
you